<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cb="http://www.cbeta.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ZW05na027">
<teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
			<title>Buddhist Texts not contained in the Tripiṭaka, Electronic version, No. a027 卷首語</title>
			<title xml:lang="zh-Hant">藏外佛教文獻數位版, No. a027 卷首語</title>
			<author>方廣錩</author>
			<respStmt>
				<resp>Electronic Version by</resp>
				<name>CBETA</name>
			</respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<editionStmt>
			<edition>XML TEI P5</edition>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp1"><resp>corrections</resp><name>orig</name></respStmt>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp2"><resp>corrections</resp><name>ZangWai</name></respStmt>
			<respStmt xml:id="resp3"><resp>corrections</resp><name>CBETA</name></respStmt>
		</editionStmt>
		<extent>1卷</extent>
		<publicationStmt>
			<idno type="CBETA">
				<idno type="canon">ZW</idno>.<idno type="vol">5</idno>.<idno type="no">a027</idno>
			</idno>
			<distributor>
				<name>中華電子佛典協會 (CBETA)</name>
				<address>
					<addrLine><email>service@cbeta.org</email></addrLine>
				</address>
			</distributor>
			<availability>
				<p>Available for non-commercial use when distributed with this header intact.</p>
			</availability>
			<date>2021-01-05 23:10:04 +0800</date>
		</publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title level="s">Buddhist Texts not contained in the Tripiṭaka</title>
				<title level="s" xml:lang="zh-Hant">藏外佛教文獻</title>
				<title level="m" xml:lang="zh-Hant">卷首語</title>
			</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	</fileDesc>
	<encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
			<p xml:lang="en" cb:type="ly">Text as provided by Mr. Fang Guangchang</p>
			<p xml:lang="zh-Hant" cb:type="ly">方廣錩大德提供</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl>
			<punctuation resp="#resp1"><p>原書標點</p></punctuation>
		</editorialDecl>
		<tagsDecl>
			<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				<tagUsage gi="rdg">
					<listWit>
						<witness xml:id="wit.cbeta">【CB】</witness>
						<witness xml:id="wit.orig">【藏外】</witness>
					</listWit>
				</tagUsage>
			</namespace>
		</tagsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	<profileDesc>
		<langUsage>
			<language ident="en">English</language>
			<language ident="zh-Hant">Chinese (Traditional)</language>
		</langUsage>
	</profileDesc>
	<revisionDesc>
		<change when="2020-12-22">
			<name>Ray Chou 周邦信</name>Created initial TEI XML P5a version with bm2p5a.py
		</change>
	</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text><body>
<milestone unit="juan" n="1"/>
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0001a" n="0001a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a01"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a02"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu type="其他" level="1">中文</cb:mulu><head>卷首語</head>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a03"/><byline cb:type="author">方廣錩</byline>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a04"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a05"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0001a0501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">《藏外佛教文獻》第一輯的卷首語曾解釋過什麼叫
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a06"/>「藏外佛教文獻」，指出「近代以來從梵文、巴利語、藏文、
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a07"/>蒙文等各種文字翻譯的佛教典籍；敦煌藏經洞保存的大
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a08"/>量佛教典籍；各地圖書館、博物館保存的未為歷代大藏
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a09"/>經所收的古代佛教典籍；正史、地方史志、叢書、類書、個
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a10"/>人文集中保存的佛教資料；與佛教有關的金石資料；近
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a11"/>現代的佛教著作與資料。上述種種均可稱為藏外佛教
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a12"/>文獻。」第一輯至第三輯比較集中地整理與發表了敦煌
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a13"/>遺書中的若干佛教文獻，而現在呈獻於讀者面前的第四
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a14"/>輯至第六輯則擬將其他方面的佛教文獻也擇要介紹若
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a15"/>干，以使讀者對所謂「藏外佛教文獻」有更加具體的印
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a16"/>象。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a17"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0001a1701" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">首先是漢譯藏文佛典。眾所周知，藏傳佛教是我國
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a18"/>三大佛教體系之一，與漢傳佛教始終交互影響。從典籍
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a19"/>交流史看，藏傳佛教典籍曾四度影響漢文佛典。第一次
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a20"/>發生在唐代，當時吐蕃統治敦煌七十餘年，一些藏文佛
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a21"/>典在敦煌被譯為漢文。數量雖然不多，但對敦煌佛教有
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a22"/>較大影響。這批典籍沒有傳到內地，因而沒有被收入漢
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a23"/>文大藏經，但幸而保存在敦煌遺書中。《藏外佛教文獻》
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a24"/>第三輯發表的《因緣心論頌》、《因緣心論釋》即屬此類。
<lb ed="ZW" n="0001a25"/>第二次發生在西夏，當時把一大批藏文佛典翻譯為漢
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0002a" n="0002a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a01"/>文。這些佛典主要在西夏流傳，也沒有能夠收入傳統的
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a02"/>大藏經，但近代以來在西夏故地屢有發現。《藏外佛教
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a03"/>文獻》第二輯發表的《八種粗重犯墮》即屬此類。如果說
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a04"/>上兩次的影響局限在一定的範圍內，則後兩次的影響則
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a05"/>廣泛得多。第三次發生在元代，從現有資料看，翻譯的
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a06"/>數量不多，且已入藏。第四次發生在近代，這一次的典
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a07"/>籍交涉，無論是深度還是廣度，都大大超出前三次。翻
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a08"/>譯的典籍無慮百十部，但至今缺乏全面、系統的收集與
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a09"/>整理。我們從中選擇了隆蓮法師於五十年代初期翻譯
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a10"/>的《入菩薩行論廣解》，刊登在第四輯，以饗讀者。隆蓮
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a11"/>法師是中國當代比丘尼中的第一人，她的這個譯本，趙
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a12"/>樸初先生在序言中已有定評。目前，不少人對藏傳密法
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a13"/>頗有興趣，坊間有關書籍出版得不少，但人言言殊。我
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a14"/>們希望本文獻的發表能促使研修者更加重視藏傳佛教
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a15"/>原始資料的學習與鑽研，以正本清源。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a16"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0002a1601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">其次是漢譯南傳佛典。古代，曾有不少南傳佛典的
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a17"/>經典被譯為漢文，但隨著佛教的衰落，南傳佛典的翻譯
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a18"/>也成為絕響。本世紀三十年代編撰《普慧藏》時，曾計劃
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a19"/>將南傳佛典譯為漢文，但因為缺乏專門人才，收入《普慧
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a20"/>藏》中的若干南傳佛典，實際是從日文轉譯的。其後，南
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a21"/>傳佛典的翻譯一直是我國佛教界、學術界注目的重點，
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a22"/>也翻譯了如《法句經》、《清淨道論》等一些典籍，但從總
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a23"/>體看，這一工作斷斷續續，沒有能夠真正展開。八十年
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a24"/>代以來，情況有所改觀，台灣佛教界致力於從日文轉譯
<lb ed="ZW" n="0002a25"/>南傳佛典，大陸學者則努力從巴利語原典直接進行翻
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0003a" n="0003a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a01"/>譯。其中特別是鄧殿臣教授發大願心，把全部力量投入
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a02"/>這一事業，精心翻譯出一批南傳典籍。正當我們為南傳
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a03"/>佛典陸續譯出而歡欣的時候，鄧殿臣教授因積勞成疾，
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a04"/>不幸逝世。這是我們的一大損失。鄧殿臣教授逝世前
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a05"/>不久，我與他已就在《藏外佛教文獻》上發表他的譯作達
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a06"/>成一致意見。在與鄧殿臣教授進行遺體告別時，我暗下
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a07"/>決心，一定要盡力把鄧殿臣教授翻譯的典籍出版出來。
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a08"/>在鄧殿臣夫人趙桐女士的大力支持下，這一願望終於實
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a09"/>現。這次刊登在第五輯上的《小誦》、《即興自說》、《大隧
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a10"/>道本生》就是鄧殿臣教授的遺作，《大念處經》則是鄧殿
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a11"/>臣教授與其夫人趙桐女士合作翻譯的。此外，鄧殿臣教
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a12"/>授翻譯的《大隧道本生經傳》已由中國佛教協會列入「法
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a13"/>音文庫」印行，《長老偈．長老尼偈》也已經由中國社會科
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a14"/>學出版社出版。當前，中國佛教界一批年輕僧人對於初
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a15"/>期佛教持有特殊而又濃厚的興趣，希望從初期佛教中找
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a16"/>到對治當今佛教界某些弊病的法門。我們希望南傳佛
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a17"/>教典籍的翻譯，對他們的這種探索能夠有所助益。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a18"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0003a1801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">使我們感到特別高興的是我們在第六輯中能夠向
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a19"/>諸位提供一批雲南阿吒力教的典籍。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a20"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0003a2001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">雲南大理等地區流傳著一種稱為「阿吒力教」的佛
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a21"/>教，這是人們早就知道的事實。但這種阿吒力教究竟屬
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a22"/>於那一個系統，過去則有著種種不同的說法，有的認為
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a23"/>它屬於印度密教系統；有的認為它屬於藏傳佛教系統；
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a24"/>有的認為它是印度密教的本土化，稱之為「滇密」。總
<lb ed="ZW" n="0003a25"/>之，雖然尚不能正確地定義，但一般均將它歸為密教。
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0004a" n="0004a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a01"/>前些年，台灣藍吉富教授在實地調查的基礎上，指出：阿
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a02"/>吒力教「與密教之間的關係，必須要重新估量。輕率地
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a03"/>將它與唐代開元間的密教、或日本、西藏的密教（或密
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a04"/>宗）劃上等號，是不精確的。」<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0004001" n="0004001"/>他認為：「阿吒力教信
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a05"/>仰，是仍在雜密階段的法術式的信仰。……似乎祇是密
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a06"/>教外殼的展示而已，並沒有吸收到密教的核心內涵。
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a07"/>……阿吒力教的教法，主要仍然來自中國的漢地佛
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a08"/>教。」<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_orig_0004002" n="0004002"/>為阿吒力教的研究指出了新的方向。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a09"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a10"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0004a1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">雲南社會科學院宗教研究所的侯沖先生經過長期
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a11"/>艱苦的努力，收集到大量的阿吒力教的典籍，在充分佔
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a12"/>有資料的基礎上，提出阿吒力教並非前人所謂的密教，
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a13"/>而是在明初教、禪、講分離政策下出現並遷移到雲南的
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a14"/>「教」派的殘餘。也就是說，所謂阿吒力教，實際是明代
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a15"/>「教」派的活化石。當然，「活化石」言者，無非是強調阿
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a16"/>吒力教實際與明代的「教」派一脈相承，並不是說阿吒力
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a17"/>教完全保持著明代「教」派的原狀，沒有任何改變。諸法
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a18"/>無常，世界上沒有永不改變的事物。例如由在家人出任
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a19"/>阿吒力，就是一個巨大的變化。總之，侯沖先生的研究
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a20"/>雖然還有不少方面需要進一步完善與仔細論證，但已使
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a21"/>我們對阿吒力教有了全新的認識，以前的疑滯一掃而
<lb ed="ZW" n="0004a22"/>空。</p>
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0005a" n="0005a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a01"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0005a0101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">侯沖先生工作的另一個意義是再次證明了科學研
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a02"/>究中努力佔有原始資料的重要性。前此人們對於阿吒
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a03"/>力教所以有種種不著邊際的看法，主要原因是沒有佔有
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a04"/>原始資料，僅滿足於二手資料的轉抄與人云亦云的摘
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a05"/>引。藍吉富先生作了實地調查，雖然由於條件有限，沒
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a06"/>有能夠實際見到多少阿吒力教的典籍，但僅憑他見到的
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a07"/>部分阿吒力教典籍的目錄及其他資料，他就敏銳地發現
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a08"/>前此的觀點是錯誤的。而侯沖先生之所以能夠發前人
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a09"/>之所未發，關鍵正在於他調查掌握與整理了一大批前人
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a10"/>沒有見到過的阿吒力教典籍。發表在第六輯的就是其
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a11"/>中的一部分。我們希望這種重視原始資料的學風能夠
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a12"/>得到切實的發揚。同時，我們也希望各文獻收藏單位能
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a13"/>夠秉承「學術者，天下之公器也」的優良傳統，為中國學
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a14"/>術文化事業的發展，作出應有的貢獻。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a15"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0005a1501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">石刻資料始終是佛教資料的一個重要組成部分。
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a16"/>石刻資料的內容非常豐富，諸如碑銘、造像題記、刻經等
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a17"/>等。古代僧人曾十分重視這些資料的收集與利用，如歷
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a18"/>代的僧傳，幾乎沒有不大量利用碑銘資料的。在《藏外
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a19"/>佛教文獻》的第四輯，我們刊登一批重慶大足的石刻資
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a20"/>料。大足石窟開創於宋代，是我國著名的石窟之一。所
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a21"/>刻諸種經文偈頌與造像，為我們瞭解與研究當時的佛教
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a22"/>提供了重要的資料。例如從第四輯所刊的大足石刻資
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a23"/>料，明顯反映出當時佛教以因果報應來勸善懲惡，用提
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a24"/>倡孝道而爭取民眾，以他力拯救為解脫號召的特色，而
<lb ed="ZW" n="0005a25"/>這正是中國民俗化佛教，或稱信仰性佛教的三個最基本
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0006a" n="0006a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a01"/>的特點。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a02"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0006a0201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">敦煌遺書中佛教文獻的整理已經成為《藏外佛教文
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a03"/>獻》的特色。由於第四、第五、第六等三輯中非敦煌資料
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a04"/>收入較多，敦煌資料的篇幅祇好相對壓縮，總計五篇。
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a05"/>第四輯刊登三階教資料兩篇，其中《佛性問答》（擬）是近
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a06"/>年在北京圖書館新發現的，特約請業露華先生予以整
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a07"/>理。本文的敦煌俗字較多，因缺乏校本對照，雖經我們
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a08"/>反覆校對多次，也曾請教過文字學方面的專家，但仍然
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a09"/>沒有把握說所有的字都已經辨認無誤，還請方家指正。
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a10"/>另一篇《大乘無盡藏法》，是信行的早期著作，日本矢吹
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a11"/>慶輝曾擬名作「信行遺文」，收錄在《三階教研究》的資料
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a12"/>篇。這次根據新發現的資料重新整理。《如來在金棺囑
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a13"/>累清淨莊嚴敬福經》是一部中國人撰寫的疑偽經，係根
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a14"/>據敦煌遺書與石刻資料綜合整理而成。該經特別強調
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a15"/>必須如法寫經造像，反映了南北朝時期僧人力圖匡正時
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a16"/>弊的努力。我想，這對於我們每一個佛教文獻整理者來
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a17"/>說，也有一定的借鑒意義。收在這三輯中的敦煌佛教文
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a18"/>獻還有第五輯中的《瑜珈師地開釋分門記》與第六輯中
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a19"/>的《進新譯大方廣佛花嚴經表（附總目）》。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a20"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0006a2001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">第四、第五、第六等三輯每輯刊登一篇研究論文。
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a21"/>其中陳金華先生的論文《傳善無畏所譯三部密教儀軌出
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a22"/>處及年代考》是他的博士論文的縮寫，文中以大量的證
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a23"/>據與嚴密的邏輯，指出傳統認為由善無畏翻譯的三部密
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a24"/>教典籍實際上並非善無畏所譯，而是日本天台宗僧人編
<lb ed="ZW" n="0006a25"/>撰的。這涉及到日本佛教台密的一系列重大問題，想必
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0007a" n="0007a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a01"/>會引起讀者的興趣。侯沖先生的《雲南阿吒力教經典及
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a02"/>其在中國佛教中的研究價值》羅列了他所收集到的五十
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a03"/>餘種阿吒力教典籍的目錄，並簡單介紹了他對雲南阿吒
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a04"/>力教研究的最新觀點，可以作為第六輯所發表的阿吒力
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a05"/>教經典的一個附錄。至於我本人的《天台教典入藏考》，
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a06"/>考察的對象雖然是天台教典的入藏，但目的卻在於探索
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a07"/>《開寶藏》的目錄結構。我曾與日本緒方香州先生約定，
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a08"/>合作進行《開寶藏》目錄的復原研究，這篇論文實際就是
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a09"/>上述研究一個部分。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a10"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0007a1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">《藏外佛教文獻》第三輯出版於1997年3月，此後
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a11"/>不斷有讀者詢問以下諸輯的出版消息。按照編委會每
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a12"/>半年出版一輯的原定計劃，我們本應在97年內出版第
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a13"/>四輯。但如上面所介紹的，此次組織的稿件絕大多數不
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a14"/>是由編委提供，故整理、編輯的進程也相應有所不同，因
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a15"/>而延誤了定稿的時間。最後，我們決定乾脆將第四輯、
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a16"/>第五輯、第六輯等三輯的稿件，作為一個整體，統籌處
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a17"/>理，一併出版。這樣，從總體來說，我們基本上仍保持半
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a18"/>年一輯的進度。今後，如果經費能夠保證，沒有其他特
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a19"/>殊情況，我們將力爭保持每半年一冊的進度。從整理內
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a20"/>容而言，除了還有部分已經整理好的阿吒力教的典籍將
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a21"/>陸續刊登外，今後的一個階段，我們將把整理的重點依
<lb ed="ZW" n="0007a22"/>然放在敦煌遺書方面。</p></cb:div>
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0008a" n="0008a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a01"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a02"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu type="其他" level="1">英文</cb:mulu><head>FOREWORD</head>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a03"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a04"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0008a0401" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">In the foreword to the first number of our <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist Texts
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a05"/> Not Contained in the Tripitaka,</foreign> I have pointed out that "Here we
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a06"/> find, for example, all kinds of Buddhist scriptures translated in
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a07"/> modern times from Sanskrit, Pali, Tibetan, Mongolian, etc.; a
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a08"/> great amount of Buddhist texts from the Dunhuang Scripture
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a09"/> Cave; ancient Buddhist texts which are kept in various libraries
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a10"/> and museums and have not yet been included in the Tripitakas of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a11"/> the various eras; Buddhist materials preserved in dynastic
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a12"/> histories, local gazetteers, classified reference books and collected
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a13"/> works of individual persons; materials on stone and bronze inscriptions;
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a14"/> Buddhist works and materials of recent dates. All the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a15"/> above-mentioned works can be called <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist texts not contained
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a16"/> in the Tripitaka.</foreign> "Our first three numbers have, relatively speaking,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a17"/> laid stress upon the collation and publication of a number of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a18"/> Buddhist texts among the surviving documents from Dunhuang,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a19"/> and the fourth to sixth numbers, which we are presenting to our
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a20"/> readers, have also selected some important Buddhist texts in other
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a21"/> areas so that our readers can get more detailed knowledge of the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a22"/> so-called <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist texts not contained in the Tripitaka.</foreign></p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a23"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0008a2301" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">Let me first talk about the Chinese translations of the Tibetan
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a24"/> Buddhist scriptures. As is well known, Tibetan Buddhism,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a25"/> being one of the three major Buddhist systems in China, and Chinese
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a26"/> Buddhism have mutually influenced each other all the time.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0008a27"/> According to the history of texts exchanges, Tibetan Buddhist
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0009a" n="0009a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a01"/> texts have exerted influence upon Chinese ones four times. The
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a02"/> earliest influence occurred during the Tang Dynasty. A number of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a03"/> Tibetan Buddhist texts were translated into Chinese in Dunhuang
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a04"/> in more than seventy years when it was under the reign of ancient
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a05"/> Tibet named Tubo. Although the number of the translations was
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a06"/> not large, they had influenced Dunhuang Buddhism greatly. Nevertheless,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a07"/> these texts have not reached the interior of our country,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a08"/> and as a result, have not been included into Chinese Tripitakas.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a09"/> Fortunately, they have been preserved among the surviving Dunhuang
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a10"/> documents. The two texts entitled <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Yin Yuan Xin Lun Song</foreign>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a11"/> and <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Yin Yuan Xin Lun Shi,</foreign> which we have published in the third
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a12"/> number of our <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist Texts Not Contained in the Tripitaka,</foreign>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a13"/> just fall into this category. The later influence occurred during the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a14"/> reign of the Western Xia, when a good number of Tibetan Buddhist
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a15"/> scriptures were translated into Chinese. Those Chinese texts
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a16"/> mainly spread in the area controlled by the Western Xia regime,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a17"/> and therefore have not been included into traditional Tripitakas.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a18"/> However, in places where the Western Xia used to be, people
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a19"/> have repeatedly found some of the texts since modern times. One
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a20"/> example is the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Ba Zhong Cu Zhong Fan Duo</foreign> published in the first
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a21"/> number of the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist Texts Not Contained in the Tripitaka.</foreign>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a22"/> Obviously, the influences exerted during the above-mentioned two
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a23"/> times were confined in a very limited area. The following two influences,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a24"/> however, have been much farther and wider. The third
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a25"/> influence occurred during the Yuan Dynasty, when, from the material
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a26"/> available now, a small number of Buddhist texts were translated
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a27"/> into Chinese and included into the Tripitakas. The fourth
<lb ed="ZW" n="0009a28"/> influence occurred in modern times, when the involved texts, in
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0010a" n="0010a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a01"/> terms of both depth and width, have greatly surpassed the first
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a02"/> three times. The number of the translated texts is about one hundred.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a03"/> Hitherto, they have not been collected and sifted completely
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a04"/> and systematically. Now, we have selected the text <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Ru Pu Sa Xin
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a05"/> Lun Guang Shi</foreign> translated by Master Longlian in early 1950's and
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a06"/> would like to offer it to our readers in the forth number of the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a07"/> <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist Texts Not Contained in the Tripitaka.</foreign> Master Longlian
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a08"/> has excelled as a bhiksuni in contemporary China, and her translation
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a09"/> has won the final judgment by Mr. Zhao Puchu in his preface
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a10"/> to it. At present, many people have showed keen interest in
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a11"/> Tibetan Tantrism, and quite a number of books in this area have
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a12"/> been published. However, among them have been found various
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a13"/> views. We hope that the publication of this text here can spur researchers
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a14"/> to pay more attention to the studies of the source material
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a15"/> of Tibetan Buddhism so as to avoid unnecessary errors.</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a16"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0010a1601" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">Then come the Chinese translated versions of the southern
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a17"/> Buddhist scriptures. In ancient times, many a southern Buddhist
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a18"/> scripture had been translated into Chinese. However, with the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a19"/> decline of Buddhism, the translation work had been suspended for
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a20"/> centuries. When the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Puhuizang</foreign> was being compiled in 1930's,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a21"/> they planned to resume the work to translate some southern Buddhist
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a22"/> scriptures into Chinese. Being in short of specialized personnel,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a23"/> some southern Buddhist scriptures, which were included into
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a24"/> the Puhuizang, had as a matter of fact been retranslated into Chinese
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a25"/> from Japanese. Since then, the translation work of the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a26"/> southern Buddhist scriptures has become a focal point for the Chinese
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a27"/> Buddhist and academic circles. Some scriptures such as the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0010a28"/> <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Fa Ju Jing</foreign> and the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Qing Jing Dao Lun</foreign> had been translated into
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0011a" n="0011a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a01"/> Chinese. However, this work, on the whole, being frequently off
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a02"/> and on, had not been really unfolded. The situation has changed
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a03"/> somewhat since 1980's. The Buddhist circles in Taiwan have
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a04"/> been engaged in translating the southern Buddhist scriptures from
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a05"/> Japanese while the Buddhist scholars in the mainland have made
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a06"/> efforts to translate the scriptures directly from the original Pali
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a07"/> texts. What is especially worth mentioning is Prof. Deng Dianchen's
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a08"/> great determination and dedication to the cause, into
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a09"/> which he had devoted all his efforts. And he had meticulously
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a10"/> translated a group of southern Buddhist scriptures. While we were
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a11"/> very delighted to see that the southern Buddhist scriptures had
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a12"/> been continuously put into Chinese we learned the sad news that
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a13"/> Prof. Deng had passed away because of constant overworking.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a14"/> His death was a great loss to our cause. Shortly before his death,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a15"/> Prof. Deng and I had agreed to publish his translations in the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a16"/> <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist Texts Not Contained in the Tripitaka.</foreign> While I was
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a17"/> paying my last respects to him I made up my mind in silence to
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a18"/> try my best to publish the scriptures that Prof. Deng had translated
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a19"/> into Chinese. Now, this wish has come true with the energetic
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a20"/> support form Mrs. Zhao Tong, Professor Deng's wife. The <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Xiao
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a21"/> Song,</foreign> the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Ji Xing Zi Shuo</foreign> and the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Da Sui Dao Ben Sheng,</foreign> which
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a22"/> are published in the fifth number of the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist Texts Not Contained
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a23"/> in the Tripitaka,</foreign> are all Prof. Deng's posthumous works,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a24"/> and the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Da Nian Chu Jing</foreign> has been jointly translated by Prof.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a25"/> Deng and Mrs. Zhao. In addition, the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Da Sui Dao Ben Sheng
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a26"/> Jing Zhuan</foreign> translated by Prof. Deng has been published and included
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a27"/> into the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">"Library of Dharma Voice"</foreign> by the Chinese Buddhist
<lb ed="ZW" n="0011a28"/> Association, and his <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Zhang Lao Ji</foreign> and <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Zhang Lao Ni Ji</foreign>
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0012a" n="0012a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a01"/> have also been put into one book and published by the Chinese Social
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a02"/> Sciences Publishing House. At present, a group of young
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a03"/> monks in Chinese Buddhist circles have been greatly interested in
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a04"/> initial Buddhism, and expect to find ways from early Buddhism to
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a05"/> cure some maladies in contemporary Buddhist circles. We hope
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a06"/> that the translations of the southern Buddhist scriptures can be
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a07"/> helpful to their exploration.</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a08"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0012a0801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">What has extremely delighted us is that we are able to offer a
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a09"/> group of scriptures of the Azhali Sect in Yunnan to our readers.</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a10"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0012a1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">The Buddhist Azhali Sect is popular in Dali and some other
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a11"/> areas in Yunnan. This has been a well-known fact for a long
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a12"/> time. Nevertheless, as to which system this Azhali Sect actually
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a13"/> belongs to, people have voiced various opinions. Some think that
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a14"/> it belongs to the system of Indian Tantrism; some feel that it belongs
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a15"/> to the system of Tibetan Buddhism; others hold that it is
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a16"/> the result of the naturalization of Indian Tantrism, and therefore
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a17"/> name it as "Yunnan Tantrism." In a word, although people are
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a18"/> still unable to define it properly, they generally attribute it to
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a19"/> Tantrism. A few years ago, Prof. Lan Jifu from Taiwan, after
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a20"/> his on-the-spot investigation there, pointed out that "the relationships
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a21"/> between the Azhali Sect and Tantrism has to be reassessed.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a22"/> It would be imprecise to indiscreetly equate the Azhali Sect with
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a23"/> the Tang Dynasty Tantrism during the reign period named
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a24"/> Kaiyuan (713-741) or Japanese and Tibetan Tantrism. <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">"(Yunnan
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a25"/> Dali De Azhali Jiao,</foreign> Zhongguo Fojiao Fanlun, Xin Wen
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a26"/> Feng Publishing Company, August 1993, p. 5) He thought that
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a27"/> "the Azhali belief is still the magic belief at the mixed period of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0012a28"/> Tantrism...It seems to be just the show of the outer casting of
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0013a" n="0013a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a01"/> Tantrism, and has not yet absorbed the kernel connotation of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a02"/> Tantrism...The doctrine of the Azhali Sect has mainly come
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a03"/> from hinterland Buddhism of China." (ibid., p. 71) He has indicated
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a04"/> a new orientation for the studies of the Azhali Sect. Mr.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a05"/> Hou Chong, who works with the Institute of Religious Studies,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a06"/> the Yunnan Social Sciences Academy, has collected a large
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a07"/> amount of the scriptures of the Azhali Sect after long-termed
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a08"/> painstaking efforts. He has put forth on the basis of his rich material
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a09"/> that the Azhali Sect is not equal to Tantrism as our predecessors
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a10"/> have stated. On the contrary, it is in fact the vestiges of the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a11"/> 'religious' sect that occurred and migrated to Yunnan in early
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a12"/> Ming Dynasty. In another word, the so-called Azhali Sect is, as a
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a13"/> matter of fact, a living fossil of the "religious" sect in the Ming
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a14"/> Dynasty. Of course, the living fossil here means to stress that the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a15"/> origin of the Azhali Sect can be traced back to the "religious" sect
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a16"/> in the Ming Dynasty. By saying so, we do not mean that the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a17"/> Azhali Sect is identical with the "religious" sect in the Ming Dynasty
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a18"/> and had not undergone any changes. All dharmas are
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a19"/> changeable, and nothing can remain intact in the world. For instance,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a20"/> it is a great change for a layman to work for the Azhali
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a21"/> Sect at present. In a word, Mr. Hou's research has cleared all
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a22"/> kinds of doubts and helped us gain completely new knowledge of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a23"/> Azhali Sect, though there is still many an aspect in his research
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a24"/> work for him to improve and perfect.</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a25"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0013a2501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">It is also significant for Mr. Hou to prove once again in his
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a26"/> work that it is of great importance to try to gain firsthand information
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a27"/> in scientific research. That people had various impractical
<lb ed="ZW" n="0013a28"/> opinions on the Azhali Sect before was mainly due to their lack of
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0014a" n="0014a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a01"/> source material and their satisfaction with copying and citing some
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a02"/> secondhand information. Mr. Lan made on-the-spot investigation
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a03"/> and yet, confined by conditions, was unable to practically see
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a04"/> many Azhali scriptures. However, just by the catalogs of partial
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a05"/> Azhali scriptures and other material he had come across, he keenly
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a06"/> found out that the before-going viewpoints were mistaken. The
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a07"/> key for Mr. Hou to discover what others had not is his investigation,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a08"/> obtainment and collation of a large amount of Azhali scriptures
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a09"/> that our predecessors had not seen. What we publish in the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a10"/> sixth number of our <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist Texts Not Contained in the Tripitaka</foreign>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a11"/> is just a part of them. We do hope that this kind of style of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a12"/> study, which attaches importance to source material, can be carried
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a13"/> forward in reality. At the same time, we also hope that various
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a14"/> working places that collect and store documents can inherit
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a15"/> the good tradition to regard "learning as a public business under
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a16"/> the heaven," and make due contributions to the development of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a17"/> Chinese academic and cultural causes.</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a18"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0014a1801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">Stone inscriptions have always been a very important part of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a19"/> Buddhist material. The content of stone inscriptions has been
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a20"/> pretty rich and full, covering tablet inscriptions, tablet records of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a21"/> statue construction and scriptures carved on stone blocks, etc..
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a22"/> Ancient monks once paid exceptional attention to the collection
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a23"/> and utilization of the material. For instance, almost all the biographies
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a24"/> of the monks in the past ages made wide use of the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a25"/> stone inscriptions. In the fourth number of the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist Texts
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a26"/> Not Contained in the Tripitaka,</foreign> we publish a group of the stone
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a27"/> inscriptions from Dazu, Sichuan. The Dazu Grottoes opened up in
<lb ed="ZW" n="0014a28"/> the Song Dynasty are among the famous Chinese grottoes. All the
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0015a" n="0015a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a01"/> carved scriptures, hymns and statues have offered important material
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a02"/> for us to get to know and make studies of the then Buddhism.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a03"/> The Dazu stone inscriptions published in the fourth number
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a04"/> of the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist Texts Not Contained in the Tripitaka,</foreign> for instance,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a05"/> have clearly reflected the features of the then Buddhism:
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a06"/> to encourage people to do good and punish evil-doers by the concept
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a07"/> of retribution; to win over people by advocating filial duty;
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a08"/> and to call on people to get salvation from other forces so as to obtain
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a09"/> their deliverance, which are just the three most fundamental
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a10"/> characteristics of the popularized Chinese Buddhism or Buddhism
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a11"/> in the nature of belief.</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a12"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0015a1201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">Collating Buddhist texts from the surviving Dunhuang books
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a13"/> has become a distinguishing feature of the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Buddhist Texts Not
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a14"/> Contained in the Tripitaka.</foreign> Since our three numbers from the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a15"/> fourth to the sixth have included a lot of non-Dunhuang material,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a16"/> we have to reduce the scope for Dunhuang material and can only
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a17"/> publish five texts concerned. The fourth number also publishes
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a18"/> two pieces of material regarding the Sanjie Sect. One of them is
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a19"/> entitled <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Fo Xing Wen Da,</foreign> discovered in the Beijing Library in recent
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a20"/> years, and we have specially requested Mr. Ye Luhua to collate
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a21"/> it. Since there are more nonstandard forms of Chinese characters
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a22"/> used in Dunhuang in the text, and we lack any collated texts
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a23"/> for us to check against, we can not say for certain that we have identified
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a24"/> all the Chinese characters without any mistakes, though
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a25"/> we have rectified the text repeatedly and have also consulted some
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a26"/> experts in philology. We, therefore, request our readers to point
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a27"/> out any mistakes they may find. Another text entitled <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Da Cheng
<lb ed="ZW" n="0015a28"/> Wu Jin Zang Fa</foreign> is an early work by Xinxing. The Japanese
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0016a" n="0016a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a01"/> scholar 矢吹慶輝 once named it as "Posthumous Work by
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a02"/> Xinxing" and included it into the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Sanjiejiao Yanjiu</foreign> as its
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a03"/> material. Now it has been collated once again according to some
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a04"/> newly-found material. <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">The Ru Lai Zai Jin Guan Zhu Lei Qing
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a05"/> Jing Zhuang Yan Jing Fu Jing</foreign> is a "doubtful and spurious work"
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a06"/> written by a Chinese, and we have collated it on the basis of some
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a07"/> surviving Dunhuang books and some stone inscription material.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a08"/> The said text emphasizes particularly that one must write a scripture
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a09"/> or build a statue according to dharma; it can also reflect the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a10"/> great efforts the monks in the Northern and Southern Dynasties
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a11"/> had made to correct the maladies of the times. I think that it is of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a12"/> certain significance for every collator of the Dunhuang Buddhist
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a13"/> literature to learn something from this. The Dunhuang Buddhist
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a14"/> texts in the three said numbers also include <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">the Yu Jia Shi Di Kai
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a15"/> Shi Fen Men Ji</foreign> in the fifth number and <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">the Jin Xin Yi Da Fang
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a16"/> Guang Fo Hua Yan Jing Biao (Fu Zong Mu)</foreign> in the sixth
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a17"/> number.</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a18"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0016a1801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">Each number from the fourth to the sixth publishes a research
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a19"/> paper. Mr. Chen Jinhua's paper entitled <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Chuan Shanwuwei
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a20"/> Suo Yi San Bu Mijiao Yigui Chuchu Ji Niandai Kao</foreign> is an
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a21"/> abridged version of his doctoral dissertation. With a vast amount
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a22"/> of evidences and tight logic, he points out in his dissertation that
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a23"/> the three Tantric scriptures are in fact not translated by Shanwuwei,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a24"/> but by a Japanese monk of the Tiantai Sect, though the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a25"/> translation of them has traditionally been attributed to the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a26"/> former. Since this has involved a series of vital matters with both
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a27"/> the Tiantai and the Tantric Sects in Japanese Buddhism, I am
<lb ed="ZW" n="0016a28"/> sure that it should interest our readers. Mr. Hou has listed more
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0017a" n="0017a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a01"/> than fifty personally collected texts belonging to the Azhali Sect in
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a02"/> his paper entitled <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Yunnan Azhalijiao Jingdian Ji Qi Zai Zhongguo
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a03"/> Fojiao Zhong De Yanjiu Jiazhi,</foreign> and he has also briefly talked
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a04"/> about his latest viewpoints on the studies of the Yunnan Azhali
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a05"/> Sect. We therefore have attached it as an appendix to the texts of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a06"/> the Azhali Sect published in our sixth number. As for my paper
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a07"/> entitled <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Tiantai Jiaodian Ruzang Kao,</foreign> I have to say that it aims
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a08"/> at probing the catalog structure of the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Kaibaozang,</foreign> though the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a09"/> object I have examined is the inclusion of the scriptures of the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a10"/> Tiantai Sect into the Tripitaka. Since I have made an appointment
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a11"/> with Mr. 緒方香州, a Japanese scholar, to cooperate with
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a12"/> each other in the program of studying and restoring the original
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a13"/> catalog of the <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">Kaibaozang,</foreign> this paper is in fact a partial result of
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a14"/> the above-mentioned research.</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a15"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0017a1501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">The third number of <foreign rend="bold" xml:lang="en">the Buddhist Texts Not Contained in
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a16"/> the Tripitaka</foreign> was published in March, 1997. Since then, our
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a17"/> readers have kept inquiring for information about the publication
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a18"/> of the following numbers. According to the original plan that one
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a19"/> new number was to be published by the editorial board every six
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a20"/> months, we should have published the fourth number in 1997.
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a21"/> However, as what we have said above, the editorial process has
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a22"/> been different from before and has been delayed, for the majority
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a23"/> of the organized contributions are not provided by our editors. Finally,
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a24"/> we decide to publish simultaneously the contributions in the
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a25"/> fourth to sixth numbers as a whole. In this way, we have basically
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a26"/> kept pace with our original plan. From now on, we shall try
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a27"/> our best to publish one number every six months, if our funds can
<lb ed="ZW" n="0017a28"/> be guaranteed and no other special matters occur unexpectedly. In
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0018a" n="0018a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0018a01"/> terms of the content, in addition to publishing continuously some
<lb ed="ZW" n="0018a02"/> of the collated texts of the Azhali Sect, we shall still lay stress on
<lb ed="ZW" n="0018a03"/> the collation of the Dunhuang surviving books.</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0018a04"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0018a05"/><byline cb:type="other">Fang Guangchang</byline>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0018a06"/><byline cb:type="other">Beijing</byline>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0018a07"/><byline cb:type="other">June 25, 1998</byline>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0018a08"/><byline cb:type="other">(Translator Liu Jian)</byline></cb:div>
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0019a" n="0019a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a01"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a02"/><cb:div type="other"><cb:mulu type="其他" level="1">日文</cb:mulu><head>序</head>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a03"/><byline cb:type="author">方廣錩</byline>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a04"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a05"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0019a0501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">《藏外佛教文獻》第一輯の序において、「藏外佛教
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a06"/>文獻」とは何であるかを、つぎのように解釋したこと
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a07"/>がある。「近代以來、サンスクリツト語．パ—リ語．チ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a08"/>ベツト語．モンゴル語等の言語に翻譯された佛教典
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a09"/>籍。敦煌藏經洞に保存された大量の佛教典籍。各地
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a10"/>の圖書館．博物館に保管された歷代大藏經未收の古代
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a11"/>佛教典籍。正史．地方史志．叢書．類書．個人の文集中
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a12"/>に含まれる佛教資料。佛教に關わる金石資料。近現
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a13"/>代の佛教著作と資料。それらすべてを『藏外佛教文
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a14"/>獻』と呼ぶ。」これまでの第一輯から第三輯までは、敦
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a15"/>煌遺書中の若干の佛教文獻を集中的に整理發表して
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a16"/>きたのであるが、今回の第四輯から第六輯において
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a17"/>は、その他の方面の佛教文獻をも若干選擇紹介して、
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a18"/>いわゆる「藏外佛教文獻」の具體的なイメ—ジをもつ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a19"/>ていただきたいとおもう。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a20"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0019a2001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">まずチベツト語佛典の漢譯版である。周知のよ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a21"/>うに、藏傳佛教はわが國の三大佛教體系のひとつで、
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a22"/>漢傳佛教とつねに影響關係にあつた。典籍の交流史
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a23"/>からみて、藏傳佛教の典籍は漢文佛典に四回影響を及
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a24"/>ぼしてきた。第一回は唐代である。當時の吐蕃が敦
<lb ed="ZW" n="0019a25"/>煌を統治した七十餘年のあいだ、敦煌においていくつ
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0020a" n="0020a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a01"/>かのチベツト語佛典が漢譯され、量的に多くはなかつ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a02"/>たけれども、敦煌佛教にとつては大きな影響力をもつ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a03"/>た。それらの典籍は內地に傳わることなく、したがつ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a04"/>て漢文大藏經に收められなかつたが、さいわいに敦煌
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a05"/>遺書中に保存された。《藏外佛教文獻》第三輯に發表
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a06"/>した《因緣心論頌》、《因緣心論釋》がすなわちそれであ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a07"/>る。第二回は西夏において、かなりの量のチベツト語
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a08"/>佛典が漢譯された。これらの佛典はおもに西夏で流
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a09"/>傳し、傳統的な大藏經には收められなかつたが、近代
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a10"/>以來、西夏の故地からしばしば發見されている。《藏
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a11"/>外佛教文獻》第二輯發表した《八種粗重犯墮》がすなわ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a12"/>ちそれである。第三回は元代であるが、現有の資料か
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a13"/>らみて、漢譯の量は少なく、また入藏している。第四
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a14"/>回は近代のことで、典籍の交涉はその深さにおいて
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a15"/>も、廣さにおいても、それまでの三回をはるかに凌駕
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a16"/>し、漢譯された典籍は無慮百十部におよぶが、今に至
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a17"/>るまで全面的系統的な收集と整理がなされていない。
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a18"/>今回そのなかから隆蓮法師が五十年代初期に翻譯し
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a19"/>た《入菩薩行論廣解》をえらび、第四輯に登載すること
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a20"/>にした。隆蓮法師は當代中國比丘尼の第一人者で、そ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a21"/>の譯本は趙樸初先生が序文に賞贊されるとおり定評
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a22"/>がある。目下、藏傳密教への關心が高まり、書籍の出
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a23"/>版もさかんであるが、評價は定まつていない。この文
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a24"/>獻の發表によつて、藏傳佛教の第一次資料が重視さ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0020a25"/>れ、學修と研究が根本から變革されることを期待する
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0021a" n="0021a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a01"/>ものである。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a02"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0021a0201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">つぎは南傳佛典の漢譯版である。南傳佛典は古
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a03"/>代から多くの經典が漢譯されてきたが、佛教の不振と
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a04"/>ともに、その翻譯も途絕えてしまつた。今世紀の三十
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a05"/>年代に《普慧藏》が編纂されたとき、南傳佛典漢譯の計
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a06"/>劃があつたが、この方面の人才不足のため、《普慧藏》
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a07"/>に收められたのは、日本語から重譯された若干の南傳
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a08"/>佛典のみであつた。その後、南傳佛典の翻譯はわが國
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a09"/>佛教界、學界の懸案事項として、《法句經》や《清淨道
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a10"/>論》などが漢譯されたものの、斷續的で、全面的展開に
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a11"/>は至らなかつた。八十年代になつて情況に變化があ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a12"/>らわれ、台灣の佛教界では日本語からの重譯に力を注
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a13"/>ぎ、大陸の學者はパ—リ—語原典から直接に漢譯する
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a14"/>努力がつづけられた。とりわけ鄧殿臣教授は全力を
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a15"/>傾けてこの一大事業に取りくむ決意を示され、南傳佛
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a16"/>典のすぐれた翻譯を續けてこられたが、まさにわれわ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a17"/>れが南傳佛典を陸續刊行しようとしたそのときに、疲
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a18"/>勞のため不幸にして逝去された。これはわれわれに
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a19"/>とつて大きな打擊であつた。教授逝去のしばらく前
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a20"/>に、わたしはその譯稿を《藏外佛教文獻》に發表する約
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a21"/>束をしていた。告別のとき、何としてもその翻譯され
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a22"/>た典籍を出版にこぎつけようと決意を固め、趙桐夫人
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a23"/>の協力を得て、いまこの悲願は實現することとなつた
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a24"/>のである。このたび第五輯に收載された《小誦》、《即
<lb ed="ZW" n="0021a25"/>興自說》、《大隧道本生》は教授の遺稿であり、《大念處
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0022a" n="0022a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a01"/>經》は教授と趙桐夫人の共譯である。このほか、教授
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a02"/>の翻譯にかかる《大隧道本生經傳》は中國佛教協會に
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a03"/>よつて法音文庫の一冊として刊行され、《長老偈》と
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a04"/>《長老尼偈》も中國社會科學出版社から出版されてい
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a05"/>る。いま中國佛教界の若い僧侶たちは、昨今の佛教界
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a06"/>にはびこる病弊を救う法門をみいだすべく、初期佛教
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a07"/>に對して強い關心を寄せている。ここに收載した南
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a08"/>傳佛教典籍の翻譯が、かれらの探索に裨益するもので
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a09"/>あることを願つている。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a10"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0022a1001" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">第六輯に雲南の阿吒力（アヂヤリ）教の典籍資料
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a11"/>を提供できたことをうれしくおもう。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a12"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0022a1201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">雲南大理に「阿吒力教」と呼ばれる佛教が流布し
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a13"/>ていることは、はやくから知られていた。しかしこの
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a14"/>阿吒力教がどの系統に屬するものであるかについて
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a15"/>は、解釋の一致を見ず、インド密教の系統、チベツト佛
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a16"/>教の系統、あるいはインド密教が中國化したものとし
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a17"/>て「滇密」と呼ばれており、嚴密な定義がなされぬま
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a18"/>ま、一般には密教に歸せられていたものである。數年
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a19"/>前、台灣の藍吉富教授は現地調查にもとづいて、阿吒
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a20"/>力教と「密教との關係は再檢討の必要があり、輕率に
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a21"/>唐代開元期の密教あるいは日本．チベツトの密教（あ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a22"/>るいは密宗）にひとしいと判斷するのは正確ではな
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a23"/>い」（《雲南大理の阿吒力教》，《中國佛教泛論》所收，新
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a24"/>文豐出版公司，1993年8月）と指摘し、「阿吒力教の信
<lb ed="ZW" n="0022a25"/>仰はなお雜密段階の法術的信仰であり、……密教的外
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0023a" n="0023a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a01"/>殼を示すにすぎず、その中心的內容を吸收してはいな
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a02"/>い。……その教法は、主要にはやはり中國內地の佛教
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a03"/>から攝取したものである」（同上）として、阿吒力教研
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a04"/>究に新しい方向を示された。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a05"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0023a0501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">雲南社會科學院宗教研究所の侯沖氏は長年にわ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a06"/>たる努力のすえ、大量の阿吒力教典籍を收集し、充分
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a07"/>な資料的基礎の上に立つて、それが從來言われていた
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a08"/>ような密教ではなく、明代初期の教禪講分離政策下に
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a09"/>出現し雲南に移つた教派の殘餘であるとの見解を出
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a10"/>された。すなわち阿吒力教とは、じつは明代教派の活
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a11"/>きた化石である。もちろん活きた化石とは言つても、
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a12"/>明代教派を相承しつつも、その原型を完全に保ち改變
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a13"/>を受けなかつたというのではない。世のすべては諸
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a14"/>法無常であつて、變化せぬものはない。たとえば在家
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a15"/>のまま阿吒力となるなどは大きな變化である。侯沖
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a16"/>氏の研究は細部の論證をへて完成されたものではな
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a17"/>いが、從前の疑滯を一掃し、阿吒力教に對するわれわ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a18"/>れの認識を一新させるものであつた。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a19"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0023a1901" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">侯沖氏の仕事のもうひとつ意義は、科學的研究に
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a20"/>おいて第一次資料を掌握することの重要性をあらた
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a21"/>めて示したことである。從來阿吒力教に關して實際
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a22"/>にそぐわない皮相な見かたが多かつたのは、第一次資
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a23"/>料にもとづかず、第二次資料や孫引きで滿足していた
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a24"/>ところに主な原因があつた。藍吉富氏の現地調查は
<lb ed="ZW" n="0023a25"/>さまざまな制約から、阿吒力教の典籍を充分收集でき
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0024a" n="0024a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a01"/>なかつたとはいえ、實見した一部の目錄やその他の資
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a02"/>料から、從來の說が誤つていたことを銳敏に察知され
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a03"/>た。侯沖氏の研究が前人を凌駕するのは、まさに從來
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a04"/>見られなかつた大量の阿吒力教典をみずから調查し
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a05"/>整理されたからに他ならない。第六輯に發表したも
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a06"/>のはその一部である。われわれはこうした第一次資
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a07"/>料を重視する學風が正當に評價繼承されることを願
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a08"/>つている。同時に、文獻を收藏する各種の機關と個人
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a09"/>が、「學術は天下の公器」というよき傳統を受け繼い
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a10"/>で、中國學術文化事業の發展に貢獻されるよう希望す
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a11"/>るものである。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a12"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0024a1201" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">石刻資料は佛教資料の重要な部分を占めてきた。
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a13"/>それは碑銘．造像題記．刻經などのさまざまな內容を
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a14"/>もつている。古代においてもその收集と利用は重視
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a15"/>され、歷代の僧傳などはみな大量の碑銘資料にもとづ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a16"/>いている。《藏外佛教文獻》第四輯に、われわれは重慶
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a17"/>の大足石刻資料を登載することにした。大足石窟は
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a18"/>宋代に創られた著名な石窟であり、刻された經文．偈
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a19"/>頌や造像は、當時の佛教を研究し理解するのに重要な
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a20"/>資料を提供してくれる。たとえば今回收錄した石刻
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a21"/>資料から、當時の佛教の因果應報と勸善懲惡、孝道の
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a22"/>提唱による民心の收攬、他力救濟による解脫信仰とい
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a23"/>つた特色を明らかに看取することができ、しかもこれ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a24"/>こそは中國の民俗化した佛教、あるいは信仰としての
<lb ed="ZW" n="0024a25"/>佛教のもつとも基本的な三大特色といつてよい。</p>
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0025a" n="0025a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a01"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0025a0101" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">敦煌遺書の佛教文獻の整理は、すでに《藏外佛教
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a02"/>文獻》の特色となつている。今回の第四、第五、第六の
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a03"/>三輯は非敦煌資料が多きを占めたので、敦煌資料の份
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a04"/>量を縮小せざるを得ず、すべて五篇の收錄となつた。
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a05"/>第四輯に收めた三階教資料二篇にうちの《佛性問答》
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a06"/>（擬題）は、近年北京圖書館で新たに發見されたもの
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a07"/>で、とくに業露華氏に整理を依賴した。その本文には
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a08"/>敦煌俗字が多く見られ、對照すべき校本もなく、何度
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a09"/>も校錄を檢討し、さらに文字學の專門家の指教をも得
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a10"/>たが、なおすべの文字に完全を期したとは言えず、讀
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a11"/>者諸賢による是正を待ちたい。もう一篇の《大乘無盡
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a12"/>藏法》は信行の初期の著作で、日本の矢吹慶輝氏が「信
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a13"/>行遺文」として《三階教研究》資料篇に收めたものであ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a14"/>る。このたび新發見の資料によつて再整理の手を加
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a15"/>えた。同じく第四輯の《如來在金棺<anchor xml:id="nkr_note_add_0025a1501" n="0025a1501"/><anchor xml:id="beg0025a1501" n="0025a1501"/>囑<anchor xml:id="end0025a1501"/>累清淨莊嚴敬福
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a16"/>經》は中國人撰述の疑偽經であるが、敦煌遺書と石刻
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a17"/>資料を綜合して整理をした。この經典が正しく寫經
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a18"/>造像すべきことをとくに強調しているのは、南北朝時
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a19"/>代の僧たちが時弊を矯正しようとした努力の表われ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a20"/>であろう。そしてこれはわれわれ佛教文獻の整理に
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a21"/>たづさわる者ひとりひとりにとつても、銘記すべきこ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a22"/>とにおもわれる。今回の三輯に收めた敦煌佛教文獻
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a23"/>には、そのほか第五輯の《瑜伽師地開釋分門記》と第六
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a24"/>輯の《進新譯大方廣佛花嚴經表（附總目）》がある。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0025a25"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0025a2501" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">第四、第五、第六の三輯それぞれに研究論文一篇
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0026a" n="0026a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a01"/>を收載する。陳金華氏の《傳善無畏所譯三部密教儀軌
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a02"/>の譯出地と年代考》は博士論文の要約で、多くの證據
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a03"/>と嚴密な論理によつて、傳統的に善無畏による翻譯と
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a04"/>されてきた三部の密教典籍がじつは善無畏所譯では
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a05"/>なく、日本の天台宗の僧による編撰であることを指摘
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a06"/>している。これは日本佛教の台密系のもつ大きな問
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a07"/>題として、讀者の興味をひくことであろう。侯沖氏の
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a08"/>《雲南阿吒力教經典とその中國佛教における研究價
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a09"/>值》は、氏の收集にかかる五十餘種の阿吒力教典籍の
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a10"/>目錄をつらね、自身の阿吒力教研究の最新見解を敘べ
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a11"/>たもので、第六輯に發表した阿吒力教經典の附錄とす
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a12"/>ることができる。拙論《天台教典入藏考》が考察の對
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a13"/>像としたのは天台教典の入藏であるが、その目的は
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a14"/>《開寶藏》目錄の構成の探索にある。かつてわたしは
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a15"/>日本の緒方香州氏と共同で《開寶藏》目錄の復原研究
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a16"/>をすすめる計劃を話しあつたが、この論文はその研究
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a17"/>の一環である。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a18"/><p xml:id="pZW05p0026a1801" style="margin-left:0em;text-indent:2em">《藏外佛教文獻》の第三輯を1997年3月に出版し
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a19"/>たあと、たびたび讀者からその後の出版についての問
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a20"/>い合わせがあつた。半年ごとに一輯を刊行するとい
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a21"/>う編輯委員會の方針に照らせば、97年內に第四輯を
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a22"/>出すはずであつたが、上に記したように、今回收錄し
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a23"/>た原稿の大部分は編輯委員會以外の手になるもので
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a24"/>あつたため、整理編輯の進行狀況も從來と異なり、定
<lb ed="ZW" n="0026a25"/>稿に遲延をきたすこととなつた。けつきよく第四、第
<pb ed="ZW" xml:id="ZW05.a027.0027a" n="0027a"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a01"/>五、第六の三輯の原稿をひとまとめにし、統一處理を
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a02"/>して同時出版することに決定した次第である。こう
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a03"/>して全體からみれば、基本的に半年一輯のペ—スを守
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a04"/>つたことになる。今後も經費が保證され、特殊事情の
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a05"/>ないかぎり、半年一輯刊行の努力をつづけてゆく所存
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a06"/>である。內容については、すでに整理のすんだ阿吒力
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a07"/>教の典籍の發表を除いて、やはり整理の重點を敦煌遺
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a08"/>書に置きたいと考えている。</p>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a09"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a10"/><byline cb:type="other">1998年6月25日記</byline>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a11"/>
<lb ed="ZW" n="0027a12"/><byline cb:type="other">（翻譯：衣川賢次）</byline></cb:div>
</body>
<back>
<cb:div type="apparatus">
<head>校註</head>
<p>
<app from="#beg0025a1501" to="#end0025a1501"><lem wit="#wit.cbeta" resp="#resp3">囑</lem><rdg wit="#wit.orig">矚</rdg></app>
</p>
</cb:div>
<cb:div type="zangwai-notes">
<head>方廣錩 校註</head>
<p>
<note n="0004001" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0004001">《雲南大理的阿吒力教》，載《中國佛教泛論》，新文豐出版公司，1993年8月，第58頁。</note>
<note n="0004002" resp="#resp2" place="foot text" type="orig" target="#nkr_note_orig_0004002">《雲南大理的阿吒力教》，載《中國佛教泛論》，新文豐出版公司，1993年8月，第71頁。</note>
</p>
</cb:div>
<cb:div type="add-notes">
<head>新增校註</head>
<p>
<note n="0025a1501" resp="#resp3" type="add" target="#nkr_note_add_0025a1501">囑【CB】，矚【藏外】</note>
</p>
</cb:div>
</back></text></TEI>